Good afternoon everyone.
My name is Dr. Mervat
Murad and I am an
internist and I am one of
the faculty at NYIT College
of Osteopasic Medicine.
Today I'm going to be
discussing with you
the part two of clinical
hypertension lecture.
You had a nice overview
with my academic
medicine scholar, Christina,
who did a good job.
And I'm going to
continue to discuss
the management section today.
I'm going to start by the
slide for session objectives,
and I expect you by the
end of this session to be
able to recognize and
apply treatment algorithm
for clinical hypertension.
You will be able to apply
the management algorithm
to a specific group of
hypertensive patients. You
also will be able to apply risk
factor modification in
conjunction to medical
treatment, and you will demonstrate
a strategy to differentiate
and treat hypertensive
emergency and urgency.
And we're going to start by
our case from the first part,
a 65-year-old black male
with history of type 2
diabetes, mellitus, and
osteoarthritis presented to
the clinic with a complaint
of headaches. He currently
takes ibuprofen and
metformin. The patient has a
family history of heart
failure and hypertension.
He lives sedentary lifestyle
and rarely exercise.
His job is stressful and
he works long hours so his
diet consists of mostly fast
food. He has been smoking
for 35 years and has two
beers a night he says he
measures his blood pressure
at home and it's 140 over
80 millimeter mercury he
brought his cuff with him
today and these are his
vitals everything is fine
except his blood pressure
is elevated 145 over 95 on
the left arm and 143 over
91 on the right arm by
automatic reading and his BMI
is 35.9 kilogram per meter
square. And it keeps this
patient in mind because
we're going to circle back
to our patient at the end of
the presentation and apply
what we learned on him.
Keep in mind about
half of all people with
hypertension are not adequately
controlled. That means
as physicians, we are
not doing a great job.
Controlling hypertension
is one of the most
important components to
prevent cardiovascular
disease because it's one
of the most preventable,
modifiable risk
factors for premature
cardiovascular disease,
more than even smoking,
diabetes, or hyperlipidemia.
For every 20 millimeter mercury
increase in systolic
blood pressure,
you have double your risk.
You double your risk for
cardiovascular death. For 10
millimeter mercury reduction
in the office systolic
blood pressure, there is
approximately 20% relative
reduction in cardiovascular
even. So you can see how
important to optimize blood
pressure control to get the
benefits and avoid troubles.
And when we treat somebody,
we start by putting
a goal for blood pressure.
And the goals are
inspired by something
called the SPRINT trial.
A SPRINT trial was a
multi-center clinical
trial, was conducted
between 2010 to 2015
and was published
in November of 2015,
where about 9,361 patients
greater than 50 years of age,
most on antihypertensive
therapy with a
systolic blood pressure
between 130 to 118 mmHg
and one or more
cardiovascular risk factor.
They divided them into
standard treatment group
with a target systolic blood
pressure less than 140,
diastolic less than 90,
versus a control-intensive
group with targeting
systolic blood pressure less
than 120 and the stoic
blood pressure less than 90.
And the key finding,
they found the intensive
treatment group significantly
reduced their cardiovascular
events by 25% and reduced
overall risk of this
by 27% when compared to
the standard treatment arm.
There was also a 4% higher
rates of serious adverse
effects from antihypertensive
in the strict control group,
which included syncope,
electrolyte abnormalities,
like hypokalemia,
hyponatremia, acute
kidney injury. However,
this association
was not statistically
significant.
And
they defined the high-risk
patient, those who are
known to have atherosclerosis,
cardiovascular disease
already, or heart failure,
or diabetes mellitus type
2. Diabetes mellitus type
2 is called cardiovascular
risk equivalent so having
diabetes automatically as if
you have chronic coronary
artery disease chronic
kidney disease also is
another risk factor age of 65
years of or greater also
consider a risk factor or if
they calculated your 10
year risk as sclerotic
cardiovascular disease score
and became 10 or more that means
you are high risk your
10-year risk is high. So
these are considered the
high-risk patients. The low
-risk patients who have none
of the above risk factors.
And
when it comes to the treatment,
the treatment
includes two domains.
Treatment with
lifestyle changes or
modifications and treatment
with pharmacotherapy.
And lifestyle
measures, you know,
will include dietary
salt restriction,
enhanced potassium
dietary intake,
exercise and weight
loss, dietary
approach to stop hypertension,
limiting alcohol intake
and management of stress.
Yes, these are all
included under lifestyle
measures. So as a
physician, your role is not
only to prescribe
medication. You are also an
educator for your patient.
You have to counsel them.
You have to educate them
about their disease,
about the benefits of
treatment, the risk
of unattended treatment
and noncompliance.
and you have to empower
them and encourage
them and ensure they
attend a healthy lifestyle
and they make some
changes which will be
helpful in the management
of their hypertension.
And also it will be
helpful in reducing
their needs for
more medication.
Nobody would like to
be on medications.
So you are not a robot
to prescribe medicine.
No, you are a health
educator, and you also
ensure to follow up,
not only one time on the
initial visit or when
you start medication.
Every step of the way,
you have to ensure
your patient is
making the necessary
lifestyle changes to
help their conditions.
You know, this table
illustrates the best proven
non-pharmacologic intervention
for prevention and
the treatment of hypertension,
you know, and I think
they are here for you.
They are self-explanatory
when it comes to the DASH
diet, low-sodium diet,
you know, less than 2 grams
and preferably less than 1,500.
milligram per day,
you know, and even in some
circumstances, at least
1,000 milligram per day
reduction in most adults.
Enhanced intake of dietary
potassium, which work
to help the excretion of
sodium, which is a culprit
in blood pressure elevation,
and also relax the
smooth muscles of the blood
vessels and help the blood
pressure but as you can
see even the benefit of
of these lifestyle changes is
more enhanced when it comes to
patient with hypertension
in contrast to
patient with normal
blood pressure everyone
you see the effect on the
systolic impact on the
systolic blood pressure is
more pronounced and more
enhanced in patients with
hypertension in contrast
to patients with normal
blood pressure so that
also illustrates the
importance of encouraging and
empowering the patient
to attend these changes.
The same here, physical
activity, you know,
a mix of aerobic and
dynamic resistance
and isometric
resistance, exercising,
exercises,
you know, and
also moderation in
Um,
so, um, I just
want to have a few
words to say regarding the, um,
the weight loss. weight
loss is a powerful factor in
a modifiable risk factor
because if you lose one kilogram
of body weight it decrease
your blood pressure by
one systolic blood pressure
by one millimeter mercury.
So if you lose 20 kilograms,
you will decrease your
systolic blood pressure
by 20 millimeter mercury,
which is significant
drop in reduction in
systolic blood pressure.
And, you know,
weight loss has been
shown to produce
the most powerful effect on the
reduction of the
systolic blood pressure,
especially when it's
sustained and it's
combined with other
lifestyle changes.
Also, combination of
a low sodium and DASH
diet resulted in
most significant
benefit, which decreases
the blood pressure,
with decrease in the
blood pressure comparable
to those obtained by
blood pressure medication
or antihypertensive, which
show you the powerful
effect of non
-pharmacological interventions
in terms of blood pressure
control, I just want to
say. I also want you to
notice the effect of all these
measures depends on the
dose, the duration, and if
they are combined together,
they are more additive and
more helpful and more
powerful in reducing the
systolic blood pressure
and reducing the overall
cardiovascular risk and decreasing
the need for medication.
And, you know, at the
time of diagnosis,
if you start someone
on medication,
you should also ensure
to implement all this
lifestyle modification
in place. And every
step of the way on the
follow-up visits, you
need to read, check,
and verify with your
patient And if they
are on the right track,
and it's ongoing
process, I just want to
say, but it's very
helpful and very promising
if you empower your
patient to do so.
So, I'm going to
transition to case one,
a 50-year-old male presented
to the clinic for a
routine follow-up, and
in the office, he has a
blood pressure of 142 over
88 millimeter mercury.
And upon subsequent
measurement,
he is diagnosed
with hypertension.
He has no other
medical conditions. He
does not smoke or
drink alcohol. His
BMI is 35 kilogram
per meter square.
Today, his blood pressure is
144 over 86 millimeter mercury.
And he asks you about
lifestyle changes that can help
him lower his blood pressure
which of the following
the lifestyle intervention
has been shown to result
in the greatest reduction in
the systolic blood pressure
a engaging in regular
aerobic physical activity
reducing b reducing dietary
sodium intake c following
dash diet d limiting alcohol
intake e weight loss of
20 kilograms so I want you
to go back to the tables
we discussed a few minutes
ago and I want you to try
to choose the right answer I
will give you a few seconds
so he is blood pressure
is 142 over 88 and he was
diagnosed with hypertension
and he does not smoke
doesn't have any other medical
condition and doesn't smoke
doesn't drink and And BMI
is 35 kilogram per meter
square, which is consistent
with stage two obesity.
And he's asking you, his
blood pressure today also is
still high. And he asked
you about the most helpful
lifestyle measure you can
do to improve his blood
pressure. and the correct
answer is based on the table I
provided a few minutes earlier
and based on the vignette
I think if he lose 20
kilograms he will be able
to reduce his systolic blood
pressure by 20 millimeter
mercury which is greater
than any other intervention
and here is the right answer
so the correct answer is e
and now we're going to talk
about the pharmacotherapy
who when to add medication
when you decide to
add medication number one
when lifestyle modification
alone are not enough in
lowering the blood pressure
you did what you did you
advise to the patient
they did their best and
still the blood pressure
is still elevated yeah so
you have to start medication
second when you block in
the patient information
and risk factors which
is listed on the slide
here for you in a calculator
called the acerosclerosis
cardiovascular disease
10 risk calculator or
MDCalc, which was constructed
by the American College
of Cardiology and the
American Heart Association.
And if the risk
score is high, 10% or
greater, they qualify
for medication.
another scenario for
pharmacotherapy is patient
doesn't have history of
cardiovascular disease and we
have low risk on the
calculator less than 10 percent
but the systolic blood
pressure is 140 or more
diastolic blood pressure is
90 or more this is a stage
2 hypertension you have
to go head and retreat.
A fourth scenario is no history
of cardiovascular disease
but they are high risk on
the calculator more than
10 percent or 10 percent or
more and the systolic blood
pressure is 130 or more or
the systolic blood pressure
80 or more. They will
qualify for pharmacotherapy.
um a last scenario they have
history of cardiovascular
they have a stroke they
had micro myocardial
infarction um so this they
already have a risk of
cardiovascular history
of cardiovascular disease
not a risk history of
cardiovascular disease and
their systolic blood
pressure is 130 or more or
diastolic blood pressure is
80 or more one or another
they qualify for medication
so these are the examples
when your patient need
pharmacotherapy so keep
them in mind um i'm not
saying you know um you
use your clinical judgment
i'm not saying keep them
you know you know keep
them in mind you know you
have you will be tested on
them but you you will you
will be able to make your
clinical judgment based on
your knowledge and decide
what your patient needs.
Pharmacotherapy usually a
lot of patients come to my
office and they told me
okay my blood pressure is
normal so I stopped taking
the medicines so you have
to to educate your patient
about the nature of their
disease and once you start
patient on medication
most of the time it's
a lifelong treatment
you know blood pressure
is a chronic condition
and controlling the
blood pressure is one of
the most beneficial and
most important thing you
can do for your patient
to prevent their
cardiovascular you know
complications and it protects
their heart and the
cardiovascular system.
So I try to educate the
patient. Blood pressure is
good because you are on the
medication. Once you stop
the medication, it may come
back with a stressor of
life and with sodium intake.
and I also educate them
about some non-modifiable
risk factors. Sometimes the
part is genetic or family
history, so you can't change
that. I know it's a
polygenic disease, but still
there is some genetic or familial
component is a possibility,
so sometimes this stuff
will never reverse so
you need some help with the
medication and for a stage
one hypertension usually
usually not every single
100% usually we start with
first-line drugs which are
called the principal
antihypertensive medication like
sciazide diuretics calcium
channel blockers ACE
inhibitors or angiotensin two
receptor blockers for a stage
two hypertension usually
recommended two first line
drugs of different classes
for example one should
be s or r and another usually
calcium channel blocker
or a sciazide diuretic
um sciazides are the
first line for
hypertensive black patient
You know, that's the
general recommendation.
Stage one, first line
drugs. Stage two,
you know, usually two first
line drugs. But, you know,
sometimes a physician
determination. We decide to
start one medication and
titrate up accordingly.
Interestingly, some
people like to start two
medications and titrate
them together. It depends.
As I said, ciazides
are the first line for
hypertensive black
population, and the reason
they get benefit from it,
they respond very well. The
reason is unclear, but in
some literature they stay
because their blood pressure
is volume-based, sodium
and water retention, and
this medication help to
decrease and excrete the sodium
and the water, and that's
why, but it's still an
unclear, definitive reason.
I second-line pharmacologic
treatment, which is
called adjunctive medication,
or medication that
is being used to treat
certain comorbid conditions
or certain conditions
the patient have, but
as they do that, they
treat the blood pressure.
I also listed the medication
for you here you know was
including the categories
the mechanism of action and
the side effect and some
examples because as a physician
you will prescribe medicines
for the rest of your
life and if you prescribe
medicine you should know
everything about the medication
so I found that a great
summary for you to know the
antihypertensive and I'm
sure it was also discussed
in pharmacology in details.
As we said there are two
types of antihypertensive
medication proper or
principal or first line
we mentioned them the
second line medication which
treat a comorbidity
with hypertension for
example ACE or ARB or beta
blocker are used also for
treating heart failure
but as they do that they
also help normalizing
the blood pressure or
lowering the blood pressure.
So they can, you know,
you hit two birds
with one stone.
For example, diabetes or
chronic kidney disease,
if you treat patient
with, for diabetic
patient with chronic
kidney disease,
and usually, you know,
patient with chronic kidney
disease and diabetes tend
to have hypertension because
all these comorbidities
have the same metabolic
pathway and insulin resistance
they have the same metabolic
background so if you give
a diabetic ACE or ARP for
to protect or slow down the
chronic kidney disease
secondary to diabetes it will
also help as a blood pressure
so it's called adjunctive
or second line
pressure so as or r
can be a first line
and it can be also
second line pharmacologic
treatment alpha
one antagonist which
is brazosin terazosin
they are mainly used
for benign prostatic
hyperplasia to treat
the PPH but as they do
that also they reduce
the blood pressure
so these are the second
line treatment not a
proper antihypertensive
like the first line therapy
keep in mind a diagnosis
can be made and the
treatment started without
further confirmatory
readings in the following
uncommon scenarios.
A patient with hypertensive
urgency or emergency,
you want to treat them. You
don't want to leave them
with a blood pressure
systolic of 180 or more, a
diastolic of 120 or more,
because they can have a
stroke. They can have a
heart attack. So you have to
treat them right away you
don't bring them to clinic
again to have another
reading you should read them
right away without a
confirmatory reading also if
a patient has a high blood
pressure but not very high
to meet the criteria for
hypertensive emergency,
but they also have evidence
of end-organ damage,
like you see left
ventricular hypertrophy on
ECG, or you look in their
fundus, and you find
them having hypertensive
retinopathy, or if
they have ischemic heart
disease on ECG or have a
history of ECG ischemic
heart disease or if
they have ischemic heart
disease or schist pain.
So this also, despite the
blood pressure, doesn't
meet the criteria for
hypertensive emergency,
but there is evidence
of end organ damage, so
you have to go and hit
and treat right away
without a confirmatory
reading to reduce the risk
and the cardiovascular
events in that patient.
I know you have gone over
the hypertensive urgency.
Hypertensive urgency means
a blood pressure of systolic
180 or more, the STOLIC
120 or more one or another
without signs or symptoms
of acute end organ
damage and you still need
to treat but you may be able
to use short acting oral
medication and then transition
the patient to long acting
for example a patient
come to clinic and you
find a blood pressure 180
over 100 you are not going
to see they don't have
any symptoms you ask about
any headache, any chest
pain. You do your blood
work. Everything is good. And
you look in their eyes. There
is no issue, no hemorrhages
or papilledema. What do
you do? Do you leave them
alone or you want to treat
them and you want to control
the blood pressure? No, I
still want to control the
blood pressure. So maybe
I give them a dose of
cholinidine 0.1 milligram
times one in clinic. I let them
settle and, you know, rest
for half an hour and repeat.
If the numbers are 160 over
110, that's fine. Then I
can give a script for
amlidipine or losartan
hydrochlorosiazide and they
start this long-acting medication
at home once a day and keep
in mind also you should
avoid decreasing the
blood pressure too fast.
Why? Not to compromise
the cerebral blood flow
because there is
something called cerebral
autoregulation, which is
the ability of the cerebral
blood vessel to dilate and
constrict over a wide range
of blood pressure changes.
You don't want to lose
that. You don't want to
lose that. You want to avoid
decreasing the cerebral blood
flow. So the first 24 hours,
the drop in the blood
pressure should be overall 25
to 30 percent. After that,
past the 24 hours, you can
drop the blood pressure
further, which is more safe
to do to avoid compromising
the cerebral blood flow.
For hypertensive emergency,
it's exactly the definition.
The same is blood pressure
of 180 or more systolic
or 120 or more diastolic,
one or another with signs
or symptoms of acute in
the organ damage. Patient at
this time having symptoms,
symptoms of severe
headache, pulmonary vision,
you know, chest pain,
flash pulmonary edema, they
are wheezing and crackling
because there is the flesh
edema, fluids around the
lungs started to accumulate
because of the extreme
elevation of the blood pressure,
or ECG shows left ventricular
hypertrophy or ischemic
heart disease criteria on
the ECG, or acute kidney
disease, elevated creatinine,
and the management here
is totally different. You
have to admit them to the
intensive care unit, and you
have to start giving them a
short-acting IV antihypertensive,
like hydrolazine, for
example, vasodilator, to
reduce the blood pressure,
and then to monitor them
over the first 24 hours.
And as we said before, avoid
sharp drop in mean arterial
pressure, no more than 20%
in the first hour, additional
5% to 10% more in the next
23 hours. then in 24 to
48 hours, you may consider
more normalization, you know,
of the blood pressure to
also avoid the impairment
of the cerebral blood flow.
And here is a diagram that, you
know, summarize what we said.
And these are the GNC-8
guidelines for hypertension
management. I think we
said it all. We spoke about
every element of the guidelines
and just, you know, the
guidelines didn't change
that much from GNC-8, but
we tended to be more strict
in terms of the goals,
as I said, because it's
proven to be more beneficial.
and as you say as
you see here every
step of the way
you ask yourself
is the patient at the
blood pressure goal if
yes you continue what
you're doing if no you go
and review the lifestyle
changes the patient is
doing and if they are
implementing them and
is there the need to
increase the medicine or
add another medicine
so that's the take-home
message from this slide
I don't want you to go
in details that's the
take-home message every
step of the way you
review with your patient
the lifestyle changes
they are doing to help
the medication if they
are doing them you
know and the blood pressure
is controlled that's
good continue if they
are not doing them
Please reinforce the
blood pressure, the non
-pharmacologic factors,
because they are proven
to be helpful, and if
they are doing them and
the blood pressure is
still elevated, you're
going to consider
increasing the medication or
adding additional
medication, and that's it.
you don't need to know
this diagram in details
you got the idea and I
will transition to a case a
50 year old black male
with no significant past
medical history present to
the clinic for an annual
checkup he is asymptomatic
his vitals include
blood pressure of 140 over
88 millimeter mercury,
heart rate is 80 beats per
minute, respiratory rate is 14,
BMI is 30, and physical
exam is otherwise
unremarkable except
for abdominal obesity.
What is the next best
tip in his management?
Start medication, bring
him in next year to
recheck, counsel regarding
lifestyle changes
and they bring in to
clinic in two weeks to
recheck blood pressure.
What do you think?
So this is a guy, a black
male, no significant
past medical history. You
find him for the first
time in your office having
a high blood pressure.
And the only risk factor,
he also have excess weight
so what do you do start
medication you need to
establish a diagnosis first
before you start medication
yes bring him in next year
to read check it's very
far you don't know what's
gonna happen in a year so
maybe see counsel regarding
the lifestyle changes and
bring it into clinic in two
weeks to read check the
blood pressure to establish
a diagnosis so that's
basically to establish a
diagnosis you need two elevated
reading on two different
occasions or more at least
two different occasions
and this is the right answer
um case continued patient
returned for blood pressure
check as advised and
the blood pressure is 145
over 90 millimeter Mercury,
who when asked about family
history, he mentioned
that his father
was diagnosed with
hypertension. If you were
to start this patient on
a medication, which of
the following would be
the most appropriate
for initial monotherapy?
Carvidalol,
lisinopril,
cloradalidone, hydrolazine
clonidine what do you
think so you know now he
is established hypertension
a black male and you are
starting him on medication
so which would be
helpful corvidalol he's a
healthy otherwise so
corvidalol usually used for
heart failure um so it's one
of the adjunct medication,
not a second-line
therapy, not a first-line
antihypertensive. So it's
not going to be the case.
Lisinopril, maybe,
but also lisinopril
in patients of color
carry the risk of
angioedema, and also is
not the first line
in black population.
Cholordalidone is a cyanide
-like diuretic, which
showed good results in
black patient population.
And maybe I will consider that.
Hydralazine is a vasodilator
and is not a first
line antihypertensive.
And the clonidine
also is centrally acting
medication and it's not
a first line. And
usually we give it in
resistant hypertension.
We add it to the first
line therapy. So I would
go with chlordalidone.
And here is the right answer.
Yeah.
We'll transition to another
case. A 45-year-old white
female with past medical
history of hypertension and
type 2 diabetes presents to
clinic for follow-up regarding
hypertension medications.
She is currently taking
metformin and hydrochlorosazide.
Her blood pressure
is 145 over 90 millimeter
mercury. Labs are unremarkable
except for mildly elevated
karyatinin. ECG in the
office is consistent with LVH,
left ventricular hypertrophy.
You decide to add
another antihypertensive
medication to her current
regimen. Which of the following
medication would be appropriate
given her history and
lab result? Calcium channel
blocker, alpha-1 blocker,
ACE inhibitor,
thiazide, aldosterone
antagonist. What do you think?
Calcium channel blocker, she
is on hydrochlorothiazide,
a thiazide diuretic.
It can be, but it's
not going to give her
the benefit because she
is diabetic with chronic
kidney disease and LVH.
So it may not be the
fairest choice in this case.
Alpha-1 blocker is mainly
used for PPH, which
is not the case, perine,
prostatic hyperplasia,
terazicin, brazosin, which is
not the case in our patient.
ACE inhibitor proven
to be beneficial in
improving the remodeling
of left ventricular
hypertrophy in patients with
hypertension, and slowing
down the progression
of chronic kidney
function in patients with
diabetes and diabetic
nephropathy, which is
the case in our patient.
So maybe ACE inhibitor will
be a good choice for her.
Sciazide, she is already
on sciazide diuretic.
You are not going
to give her another
sciazide diuretic.
That will cause more
troubles and more
electrolyte disturbances.
Aldosterone antagonist is
another type of diuretics,
potassium sparing diuretics,
but in this case, she
has chronic kidney disease,
and you give her another
different diuretic in
addition to what she has,
it may also jeopardize
the kidney function more.
So it's not the right
choice, and it may give
her also more electrolyte
disturbances. So I
would, the correct answer
is ACE inhibitor C.
Another case, a 65-year
-old female present to
the hospital from his
doctor's office with a
headache that started
this morning and got
worse. His blood pressure
is 190 over 130 in the
right arm and 189 over
130 in the left arm.
BUN is 60, creatinine is 2,
which is high. On physical
exam, you see that photo
on the right-hand side.
What is the next step in
the management? So this
patient came with extreme
blood pressure elevation,
which is consistent
with end organ damage,
chronic kidney
elevated creatinine,
acute kidney disease maybe,
and papilledema, which is
seen here, papilledema,
you know, of the
optic desk, optic cup.
So that's a sign of
hypertensive emergency.
So you have to treat right
away. So the options are A,
start the patient on a short
-acting oral medication,
start IV treatment to
lower the blood pressure
to 150 over 90 millimeter
ASAP, Get an MRI,
test for secondary
causes of hypertension,
start IV treatment to lower
blood pressure to 160 over
110 millimeter mercury
over 24 hours. What do you
think? That patient with
hypertensive emergency. So you
want to treat them right
away. So you are not going
to wait to give them a short
-acting oral medication.
That's the case in
hypertensive urgency, not
emergency. You are also not
going to lower the blood
pressure very fast to avoid
compromising the cerebral
blood flow because
patient may get stroke. So
you are not going to start
IV treatment to lower
blood pressure to 150 over
90 ASAP. You cannot do
that. Get an MRI. MRI is
a time-consuming imaging.
The proper one will be,
and I'm sure this patient
will get it because she
presented with headache
and signs, he presented
with headache and has
signs of hypertensive
encephalopathy. So he may be
qualified for CT scan,
which is a fast modality
to exclude stroke or
hypertensive encephalopathy.
But not MRI. So MRI
is not the right
choice. Test for
secondary causes of
hypertension. There
is no time to do that.
Later maybe that will be
an appropriate further
workup. But for now, you
need to start IV treatment to
lower the blood pressure
to a reasonable goal, which
is 160 over 110 millimeter
mercury over 24 hours.
And then you're going
to lower further
afterwards to avoid
compromising the cerebral
blood flow. So E will
be the right answer.
And here is the right
answer. And I want to go
back to our patient i did
not forget our first case
from the first lecture
because we're gonna apply
what we learned on that
patient before we leave
one second i am sorry to
go back all the way yeah so
how we're gonna manage
this patient This is a 65
demographic black male, has
some risk factors, diabetes,
type 2 diabetes,
and he had headache,
and, you know,
he is, has,
you know, family
history, other risk
factors, family history
of heart failure,
heart disease, and
hypertension. so it runs in his
family, has a sedentary
lifestyle, he doesn't exercise,
his job is stressful,
he works longer hours,
his diet is bad, fast
food, and he also is
smoking and drink
alcohol on daily basis,
and his blood pressure is
high, consistent with stage
stage two hypertension he
brought his cuff with him
today so we want to show
you that the blood pressure
is not doing well so how
you want to approach this
patient so we're going to
talk about the two domains
first we're going to do
lifestyle changes we're going to
counsel him regarding healthy
diet and exercise we're
going to advise him to cut
down on smoking smoking
It doesn't produce
a fast effect on the
blood pressure, but
also on long-term,
it decrees the
cardiovascular risk.
And also, I'm going to advise
him to cut down
on daily alcohol.
He should be a
responsible drinker,
you know, or moderate
alcohol intake.
He should also improve
his food intake.
Maybe we'll counsel
him on dash diet
because he eat most
of the time fast food.
He also work
longer hours and he
is a stressor,
he has a burnout,
work burnout.
So we should advise
him on meditation,
yoga, work-life balance,
and help him manage his
stress or speak even to a
therapist or a counselor to
help him to create a balance
between work and life.
So, we're going to help him,
we're going to also, you know,
help him to optimize his
blood sugar control if the
metformin is not adequate
to control his blood sugar.
And we're going to
also maybe counsel him
regarding the use of
NSAIDs, because NSAIDs also
can increase the blood
pressure medication,
the blood pressure reading,
because it worked by
antagonizing the renin
-angiotensin-aldosterone system,
basically antagonize
the mechanism,
the antihypertensive work.
So maybe Tylenol extra
strength will be a better
choice for him, or we
can also tab on other
headache medication which
doesn't contribute to
blood pressure elevation.
In terms of the medication,
he is a black male.
We can do one of two things.
We said maybe stage two
patient will benefit from
two medication at a time.
If you want to be gentle
and conservative, you
may start him on
hydrochlorosiazide or chlorozydone,
since hydrochlorosiazide
or chlorozydone are
proven to be beneficial
in black patient, and the
response is good. or if
you want to start him
on two medication, you
can maybe start him on a
small dose ARB with calcium
channel blocker, two
medication at one time
and titrate as warranted.
You know, I think ARB
will be a better choice
than, a safer choice, I
want to say, not a better
because some black population
will encounter some
single angioedema, which
is a serious side effect
from ACE, and we have to
transition them to ARP,
angiotensin receptor
to blockers.
We're going to also advise
him to return to our
office maybe in two to
three weeks for blood
pressure recheck, and we're
going to also reinforce
the lifestyle measures,
and we see his updates,
where he is in the
process, and we're going
to monitor him and to
ensure, you know, he is
compliant with medication
and lifestyle measures.
And I believe I am going to go
back to the summary
slide, which
is exactly, you know,
So summarize, exercise
and diet, DASH diet have
a significant impact
on when it comes to
controlling hypertension.
ACE or calcium channel
blocker or sciazides
are the first line
treatment for hypertension.
Goal and treatment differ
depends on the risk factors
and the comorbidities of
the patient, and we said
that high risk versus low
risk patient. so we are more
strict with the high-risk
patient in terms of blood
pressure goals. Be aware
of resistant hypertension
and understand that
hypertension specialists should
be consulted if the patient
is on three medication,
one of them diuretic at
the best tolerated, most
tolerated dose, or on four
medication, controlled
on four medication. maybe
another reason behind
the blood pressure
elevation, like renal artery
stenosis or fibromuscular
dysplasia. Recognize
signs and symptoms that
distinguish hypertensive
emergency from urgency.
And here are my references.
And I hope you enjoyed
the lecture. And if you
have any question please
feel free to reach
out to me my email is m
like mary my last name m
morad at nyit.edu i
will be happy to assist
you in any way i can i'm
always um checking my
emails so this will be
the first way to get me.
Again, have a nice afternoon
and stay well. Bye-bye.